Leonard Scott Union Prevention and Counter-Union Campaign Consulting Files 6474
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Leonard Scott Union Prevention and Counter-Union Campaign Consulting Files
1966-2013
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Scott, Leonard
West Coast Industrial Relations Association (WCIRA)
6474
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Records (documents).
This collection consists of union-prevention training materials, files from counter-union campaigns, and other anti-union consulting records. These records were collected by Leonard C. Scott, a Cornell University, ILR School alumnus and human resources consultant. The materials were collected between 1966 and 2013. Leonard C. Scott specialized in combatting union organizing and in developing programs to keep companies operating in a union-free environment. The collection consists of various anti-union campaign material from various companies and relevant articles.
9754412
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, November 30, 2016
EAD encoding:
Elizabeth Parker, July 18, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Leonard C. Scott was a human resources professional and an anti-union advocate, based mostly in Illinois and later Texas. He had been a corporate human resources and labor relations executive, providing consulting services to a broad range of American and foreign owned companies. He also taught business and human resources management courses at several colleges. He appeared on a number of radio talk shows, wrote articles in various magazines and made presentations at national and international professional and trade associations.
Leonard C. Scott received a B.A. in Economics from the University of Illinois, a Master's degree in Economics from Northwestern University, and was a PhD candidate at Cornell University's ILR School. He served as a graduate student assistant to Prof. Milton R. Konvitz, in 1963, but he did not complete his doctoral program.
During his career, Mr. Scott worked in the field of human resources consulting and union prevention/counter-union services. He was the Labor Relations Manager at Union Carbide's Crystal Products Plant in East Chicago, Indiana, during the collective bargaining strike (1966-1967), against Union Carbide Corporation by the Chemical Workers Union, the United Steel Workers Union, and the Oil, Chemical, and Atomic Workers Union (OCAW). He developed an "Inclusive Capitalism" program at the PSN Corporation, a manufacturer of industrial fasteners, in Elk Grove, Illinois. In the 1970s, Mr. Scott worked for West Coast Industrial Relations Association (WCIRA), the second largest anti-union firm during the 1970s and 1980s. He was the head of its Mid-America Employee Relations Association (MERA) division in Oak Brook, Illinois, until WCIRA ceased operations and MERA went out of business. At that time, he continued to operate a consulting business under Leonard Scott & Company in the areas of union prevention, executive search, and human resource consulting for foreign companies starting up in the US. Domestically, he collaborated with a number of companies in various industries, such as healthcare, energy, and food. Several of his major foreign company clients were Arthur Young & Co. (UK), Marazzi Ceramica, (Italy), Ericsson Telecom (Sweden), Uddeholm Steel (Sweden), and Delta Daily Foods (Canada).
Mr. Scott believed that corporate human resources could help employees. However, in the 1980s, 1990s and beyond, he discovered that more and more manufacturers, who successfully blocked union organizing among their employees, eschewed the recommendations of their union avoidance campaign consultants. He also found that the in-house human resources managers failed to set up positive employee relations programs after they successfully defeated unionization attempts. Instead, manufacturing companies began to offshore their production operations, as well as to reduce the number of employees.
Mr. Scott's parents were union members in the 1920s and 30s in Chicago, IL. His mother, Lottie Czarnecki, was a member of Local 1031, International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers A.F. of L. His father, Thaddes Czarnecki, was an organizer for the American Bakery & Confectionery Workers' International Union AFL-CIO in the 1930s.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1966-2013
Bulk dates: 1975-1980
The collection consists of reports, questionnaires, letters, programs, articles and newspaper clippings, memorandums, books, event records, handwritten notes, and pamphlets related to counter-union campaign activities, mostly between 1966 and 1985. The collection documents Scott's important counter-union campaigns, with examples of similar cases.
More specifically, the collection contains a copy of the Daily Strike Record of the OCAW strike at the Union Carbide Crystal Products Plant in East Chicago, Indiana, with relevant announcements and handwritten notes. The collection also includes a letter, news clippings and other records related to the Hood River Memorial Hospital counter-union campaign. One of the significant organizations represented in these files is the West Coast Industrial Relations Association (WCIRA). The collection contains records related to the WCIRA Industrial Relations Audit program; records about the organization's campaign procedures; copies of WCIRA reports to clients on establishing positive employee relations programs; WCIRA materials used in counter-union campaign marked "Campaign Information;" and, WCIRA internal materials sent from headquarters to consultants in the field marked "Campaigns."
The collection also contains pamphlets about the role of a supervisor and pressures in today's workplace; explanation of the legal case Sioux Products v. National Labor Relations Board; memoranda, notes, correspondence, articles, and other records from the Law Offices of Warren C. Ogden. There are also memoranda, newspaper clippings, and other records of counter-union activities in different industries. The collection also includes reports of sessions with employees to air complaints, called "ventilation meetings" for various companies. Moreover, there is a variety of counter-union campaign material samples, created by Leonard Scott and Company. Finally, the collection includes two books, Leonard C. Scott wrote about the PSN Corporation's "Inclusive Capitalism" program, as well as miscellaneous newspaper clippings and articles regarding counter-union campaigns, union avoidance, strikes and more.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Union busting; United States. National Labor Relations Act; Labor unions -- Organizing; Supervisors; Strikes; Chemical industry -- Employees -- Labor unions; Hospitals -- Employees; Hispanic American professional employees; Chemical workers -- United States; Human Resources; Industrial relations -- Research -- United States; Personnel management -- United States; Anti-union campaign; Inclusive Capitalism; Scott, Leonard; Long, Fred.; Ogden, Warren C.; West Coast Industrial Relations Association (WCIRA); Leonard Scott and Company; United States. National Labor Relations Board.; Oil, Chemical, and Atomic Workers International Union; Labor Relations Reporters.; Office and Professional Employees International Union.; Labor Relations Association. Inc.; Industrial Relations, Inc.
9754412
- Carbide Strike Record, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: Records of Events Following The Company's Presentation of its Final Position, 1966-1967; Text (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Eight month long (August 18, 1966 to March 27, 1967) coordinated bargaining strike against Union Carbide Corporation by the Chemical Workers Union, the United Steel Workers Union, and the Oil, Chemical, and Atomic Workers Union (OCAW)..
  - Item 2: Announcements During The Strike: Announcement #1, 1966; Text (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Announcement about the beginning of a strike. Involved parties: ARA Company; Oxygen Plant Company, Speedway Factory, National Labor Relations Board (NLRB).
  - Item 3: Introduction: This book tells the hour by hour story of an eight month long strike, 1966-1967; Text (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Typed, drafted notes on Carbide Strike and negotiations between the company and the unions..
- Hood River Memorial Hospital Campaign Information (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: West Coast Industrial Relations Association, INC (WCIRA) Campaign Procedures, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Table of Contents: Pre-campaign activities and preparations, NLRB; Planning; Strategy; Legal considerations; Meetings and other material..
  - Item 2: Hood River Memorial Hospital Campaign Information (HRMH), 1976; Letter (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Letter to the Hood River Memorial Hospital with promotional material against the Union (November 9, 1976). Attachments: Official announcement of the company to the employees about an attached Memorandum and Agreement by and between Retail Clerks Union, Local 800 and HRMH Employees. Additional, supportive material: A Personalized Bank-Book of Benefits For Valley Hospital Employees. A record with title "Negotiations: What is truth?" An example from a similar case with title "What the U.A.W. did for Robertshaw Employees." Memos to Fellows Employees from the PAN American Gyro-Tex. The Constitution of International Union, United Steelworkers of America. Facts about Negotiations and The Teamsters. Newspaper clippings with related cases and other negotiation papers.
- WCIRA Industrial Relations Audit (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: WCIRA Industrial Relations Audit, Text (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Confidential Pre-Audit Questionnaire.
  - Item 2: West Coast Industrial Relations Association, Inc. (WCIRA), 1979; Letter (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Correspondence from the Executive Vice President of the WCIRA to the Director of Personnel of Hoag Memorial Hospital Presbyterian in Newport Beach, California (February 28, 1979). It presents a Three-Phase Employee Relations Audit Program developed by WRICA, focused on health care and industrial facilities throughout the US..
  - Item 3: Report to the Vice President of the Fluorocarbon Company, in Sunnyvale, CA, 1977; Text (Box 1, Folder 3)
    It summarizes WCIRA's findings on the evaluation of Fabricators Division, Seattle, Washington. July 5, 1977.
- Course Syllabus for "The Role of the Supervisor" (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: Course Syllabus for The Role of the Supervisor, 1978; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Published by the West Coast Industrial Relations (WCIR), Center for Management and Development.
- The Role of the Supervisor (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: The Role of the Supervisor: a guide, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Training manual for supervisors, containing sections: Interviewing and Selection; Discipline and Discharge; Managing the Marginal Employee; Motivation; Training and Orientation; Performance Appraisal.
- Warren Ogden Memos (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Item 1: Memo on The Use of Struksnes Polls to Test Majority Status, 1979; Text (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Memorandum to all consultants, presenting the ways an employer is able to determine a union's majority status. May 21, 1979..
  - Item 2: Preventing Needless Strikes: A Report, 1978; Text (Box 1, Folder 6)
    September 16, 1978.
  - Item 3: Handwritten notes on Counter-Union Campaign, 2018; Text (Box 1, Folder 6)
    September 24, 2018.
  - Item 4: 30-cent COLA Payment Triggers Pay Cutbacks At Struggling A&P; Sun Election to replace Union, 1981; News clipping (Box 1, Folder 6)
    January 12, 1981.
  - Item 5: Unilateral Implementation Of Wage And Benefit Changes, 1979; Text (Box 1, Folder 6)
    A Memorandum to all consultants related to the employers' negotiations with the Union, with an example case. June 18, 1979.
  - Item 6: Bargaining-From-Scratch Statements, 1979; Text (Box 1, Folder 6)
    A Memorandum to all consultants related to Bargaining-From-Scratch Statements, as a technique to prevent employers from violate the Labor Management Relations Act (LMRA), with relevant documentation. April 10, 1979.
  - Item 7: The Declining Market for Unionization, 1978; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Published by The Conference Board, Information Bulletin. August 1974, number 44..
  - Item 8: Supervisor's Guide In A Strike, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Item 9: Tolling Employer Back Pay Liability, 1978; Text (Box 1, Folder 6)
    A Memorandum to all consultants on how to toll employers' back pay liability. September 12, 1978..
  - Item 10: Duty of Employers to meet and confer under Fiberboard Case, Letter (Box 1, Folder 6)
    To all WCIRA Consultants (ca. 1980).
  - Item 11: Bargaining Tactics, 1979; Letter (Box 1, Folder 6)
    To all WCIRA Consultants. With an attached 102 LRRM about the Arrow Molded Plastics Inc., from Ohio.
  - Item 12: Memorandum: Remedies for Violation of National Labor Relations Act, 1979; Letter (Box 1, Folder 6)
    With a name list with all consultants distribution. July 20, 1979.
  - Item 13: Memorandum: The Blocking Charge Rule, 1979; Letter (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Schlachter Meat Company. August 26, 1978.
- Other Memos (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Item 1: A memorandum with attached articles on Modern Management Methods, Seybath, Shaw, Fairweather and Geraldson, as well as unions., 1979; Letter (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Included articles: Hauser, Dedra. "The Union-Busting Hustle: Pinkertons with bats have been replaced by consultants with psychological weapons," The New Republic, August 25, 1979; Warren, James, Kelly J. Brian. "Law memo," Chicago Sun Times, July 16, 1979; "AFL-CIO Attack, On Labor Consultants," Labor Relations Reporters. April 16, 1979.
  - Item 2: Counter-Organizational Track record in Business / Industry., 1975-1977; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 7)
    A list of industries, with location information and when defeated/or stopped drive the relevant union.
  - Item 3: The Mafia Tightens Its Grip on the Grip on the Teamsters, 1974; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Teamsters Local 295 (New York, NY), relation to New York Mafia.
  - Item 4: Correspondence re rehiring a former employee, 1979; Letter (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Handwritten Letter.
  - Item 5: Memorandum, 1979; Letter (Box 1, Folder 7)
    In re Misrepresentations Prior to Election.
  - Item 6: Johnny Poultry Act, 1979; Letter (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Correspondence with an attached statement from the company that protects employees' rights in participating or not, in an investigation conducted by the Company..
  - Item 7: Memorandum re ways to legally request employees in the hospital their intent to continue working notwithstanding a strike., 1979; Letter (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Attached, the example of the Johnny Poultry Act..
  - Item 8: Inadequate Representation and Unfunded Pension Liabilities, 1979; Letter (Box 1, Folder 7)
    To all Consultants and Attorneys, with an attached distribution list. Attached articles: "On trial: A union's fairness," Business Week, August 13, 1979. "Unfunded Pension Liabilities: A Rein On Their Growth- For Now," Business Week, August 13, 1979..
- Pressures in Today's Workplace (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Item 1: Pressures in Today's Workplace: Oversight Hearings Before The Subcommittee On Labor-Management Relations Of The Committee On Education And Labor., 1980; Text (Box 1, Folder 8)
    House of Representatives, Ninety-sixth Congress, First and Second Session. Washington: U.S. G.P.O., 1980.
- Advertising Posters Employee Ventilation and Employee Relations Program Audit (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Item 1: Correspondence to John Lamers, Vice President of the Advertising Posters Company, 1981; Letter (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Regarding hiring employees and job posting. February 3, 1981..
  - Item 2: Advertising Posters Company, Inc. Employee Ventilation and Employee Relations Program Audit, 1980; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Table of Content: Supervisor Perception; (Hispanic and Non-Hispanic) Employee Complaints and Perceptions; Ventilation Recap & Findings; Recommendation.
- Sioux Products vs. NLRB (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Item 1: Explanation of the Sioux Products, Inc.v. NLRB Case Decided by the U.S. Court of Appeals, Seventh Circuit, on March 24, 1983., 2016; Letter (Box 1, Folder 10)
    A letter from Leonard Scott to Cheryl Beredo (the director of Kheel Center in 2016), with photocopies of the Explanation of the Sioux Products, Inc.v. NLRB. 703 Federal Reporter, 2d Series. pp.1010- 1019..
- Bloom Companies Benefit Communication and Employee Ventilation (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Item 1: Bloom Companies: Benefits Communication and Employee Ventilation Assignment, Feedback Session., 1984; Text (Box 1, Folder 11)
    This study includes Employees Concerns, Recommendations and Action Plan and Benefits to Company..
  - Item 2: Bloom Companies: Benefits Communication and Employee Ventilation Assignment, Final Report., 1984; Text (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Full Version.
- WCIRA Campaign Procedures and What Employers Can and Cannot Do (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 1: Tentative Schedule for Opening Phase of Campaign, Text (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 2: What Managers Can't Do, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 3: Labor Board Ruling Bar Millions of Workers from Forming Unions, 2006; News clipping (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 4: Anti-Union promotional material on what managers should not do, tips and recommendations., 1978; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 12)
    An additional copy of the article: Fulmer E. William. "When employees want to oust their union". Harvard Business Review. March- April 1978. pp. 164-170..
  - Item 5: Handwritten note, Text (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 6: Card Signing Talk, Text (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 7: WCIRA Campaign Procedure, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 8: Winning NLRB Elections, 1960-1979; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 12)
    All unions.
  - Item 9: UARCO INC. Decision of NLRB. 88 LRRM., Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 12)
    pp. 1103-1105.
  - Item 10: NLRB v. Rollins Telecasting, INC. 88 LRRM., Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 12)
    pp. 2737-2739.
  - Item 11: Campaign Checklist, Text (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Handwritten notes.
  - Item 12: WCIRA As A Campaign Issue, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 13: Number of RM and RD Elections, 1960-1978; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 14: Typical Campaign Issues WCIRA Can Expect To Face In The 1980s, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 15: Profile of WCIRA Consultant, Text (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 16: Union Organizing Techniques, Text (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Campaign Information (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Item 1: Handwritten notes, Text (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Item 2: The Pimsletter on Business Strategy, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Number 6. Unions and Profits.
  - Item 3: 25th Hour Speech, Text (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Item 4: Negociacin: Cual Es La Verdad?, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Spanish language pamphlet.
  - Item 5: Why Labor Unions Have Grown Reluctant To Use the S Word. Global, High-Tech Economy Makes Striking Riskier As Membership Declines. A Sense of Shared Purpose, 1999; News clipping (Box 1, Folder 13)
    The Wall Street Journal. Vol.Civ. No. 118. 1999, December 17.
  - Item 6: What Would A Strike Cost You?, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Item 7: The Most Important Job Quiz You May Ever Answer, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Item 8: Memorandum of Agreement By and Between Steelworkers International Union and Employees of Resol Manufacturing Corp., Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Item 9: Look Out Below, 1973; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Union Busting CheckList. Photocopies. September 1973.
  - Item 10: Insurances will protect traveler if airline declares bankruptcy, News clipping (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Item 11: Soviets: Reagan caused hatred, 1983; News clipping (Box 1, Folder 13)
    The El Paso Times, November 10, 1983..
  - Item 12: 10,000 stand in line for 46 jobs, News clipping (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Buffalo, NY.
  - Item 13: You Just Cant Win Dept.: Firm Sues Workers for Failing to Strike, News clipping (Box 1, Folder 13)
    The Wall Street Journal. Youngstown, Ohio.
  - Item 14: Untitled clipping about the Reagan administration, 1983; News clipping (Box 1, Folder 13)
    The Wall Street Journal. June 6, 1983..
- Articles and New Clippings (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Item 1: Search For: Presidents labor management advisory committee in Lycos.net., Text (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Website search results.
  - Item 2: Analysis, 1979; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Reversal of NLRB's Certification of "Craft-Like" Bargaining Unit.
  - Item 3: Labor Relations, 1979; News clipping (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Article in Personnel Journal, in December 1979 with a handwritten note: Copy to Consultants. December 1979.
  - Item 4: Union Proficiency Study Boomerangs on Pay Issue; A Labor Trophy, Slightly Tainted, 1979; News clipping (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Mostly photocopies; Los Angeles Times; Union-financed study.
  - Item 5: BLS Report On Labor Union And Employee Association Membership, 1973, 1979; News clipping (Box 1, Folder 14)
    October 4, 1979.
  - Item 6: I Said Wed Never Have A Union, 1980; News clipping (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Ritcahrdson Brothers Co. Sheboygan Falls, WI. December 19, 1979.
  - Item 7: News Briefs: Congressional Review of EEO Reorganization Plan, 1978; News clipping (Box 1, Folder 14)
    April 28, 1978.
  - Item 8: For Your Own Protection: Implications of Signing A Union Authorization Card, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Item 9: Winning Organizational Campaigns, Communicating Adverse Consequences of Unionism: The Boards View, News clipping (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Photocopy of an article; Union-Free enviroment.
  - Item 10: Fire Department Fights Strife Long After Strike, 1980; News clipping (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Chicago Tribune. November 17, 1980.
  - Item 11: Why Unions Are Losing: The Role Of Todays Labor Consultants, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Item 12: Membership And Local Statistics, 1970-1978; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Union Organizing facts, NLRB Elections by Union.
  - Item 13: Union Organizers: Savvy Strategists, 1978; News clipping (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Photocopy; Industrial Week. August 8, 1978.
  - Item 14: Negociaciones: Que Es La Verdad?, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Spanish language pamphlet in re Steelworkers' Elections on September 12, 1979.
  - Item 15: Productivity, Violence, 1975-1979; News clipping (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Various newspaper articles (photocopies). Campaign material about productivity, violence, strikes and labor disputes. New Orleans, Ohio, California, Kansas, Oregon, Texas..
  - Item 16: Objectionable Conduct, 1979; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Dominician Cruz Hospital Election, Liberty Vinyl Elections. Fred Long was the founder of WCIRA. July 17, 1979.
  - Item 17: Negotiations: What's The Truth?, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Against Teamsters and the election held on June 27, 1980..
  - Item 18: What Has Happened So far?, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 14)
    About union "organizing processes.".
  - Item 19: Negotiations: What's The Truth?, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 14)
    What will happen if they vote in at Sioux Products..
  - Item 20: Guarantee: The U.A.W. Hereby Guarantees, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Photocopy.
  - Item 21: What's In It For The Union And What The Union Promises You, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 14)
- National Labor Relations Board (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Item 1: Your Government Conducts an Election. For you- on the job., Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Information for Voters in Labor Board Elections.
  - Item 2: Local 745, IBT v NLRB, Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 15)